Good morning everybody and welcome to
Moonshots Live, our inaugural event.
>> Yeah,
it is such an awesome treat to have all
of you here and get a chance to meet you
guys. Uh our smiling muscles are
exhausted from this morning, but I think
we're going to be going throughout the
day. On behalf of Dave Blondon, AWG,
Seem, and Emod, it is an awesome
pleasure to have you guys here. Yeah,
give it up.
So, we're going to talk about this, but
our mission is to keep you hopeful,
optimistic, and to inspire you to find
your massive transformative purpose, to
choose your moonshot, and to make it
happen.
Right? It's this is life during the
singularity. It's never going to be any
slower. We have the opportunity each and
every one of us to make the future what
we desire. The future is not happening
to us. It's what we create. Right? Ours
is the ability given these superhero
technologies enabling us to build,
create, and steer that future. Right? AI
is not a hand grenade. It's a jetpack.
It's an opportunity for us to find
problems and solve problems. You know, I
define an entrepreneur as someone who
finds problems and solve problems. And
the more entrepreneurs on the planet,
the more problems get solved. Do we have
challenges? Of course. But that's what
we humans do. We find the challenges and
we fix them. Please remember that. My
hope for you, each and every one of you
here today, is to find extraordinary
co-founders here in this room. To find
those individuals who share your
purpose, design moonshots, and execute
on them. The ability has never been
faster and more capable than it is
today.
So, by the end of today, if you're not
clear what your purpose is, please dig
in to find it. And walk away with at
least one sentence in your mind. This is
what I'm going to build. This is the
problem I'm going to solve. And then
today or tonight, find three people and
speak that statement out loud. When you
speak it out loud, you make it real. And
guess what? the person you talk to may
be your next co-founder, maybe your next
funer, maybe your next partner. Take the
time to do that because you can. And
this is the room where magic is going to
happen.
All right. Uh it's time to introduce my
moonshot mates. Let's roll the video.
>> The question is, how do you build? How
do you make things better? People who
were already in the ecosystem now have a
super intelligence at their beck and
call. The story line that we're
capturing here will last for millennia.
>> As a mathematician, GPT 5.6 Pro is the
only quality math model.
>> All of this automation and AI enablement
and cognitive abundance allows us to be
deeply deeply deeply creative.
>> Video Gen combined with AI is a very
powerful force.
>> A year from today, we'll all be like,
"Wow, remember how slow it was?"
Please give a warm welcome to the
moonshot mates.
>> All right, I'm going to call them out.
I'm going to call them out one at a
time.
Our Afghan warlord, Selene Miso,
our super intelligence, Alex Gross.
our giant Immad Gust
>> and my fraternity brother.
Gentlemen,
first of all, I did hug Alex and he is
somewhat physically real.
>> You didn't pinch my should be a robot.
He is real.
>> I'm a real boy.
>> Yes.
>> Uh first of all, wasn't last night
amazing? How about give it up for
William Shatner? Huh?
>> Unbelievable.
>> You know, uh I'm just blown away by his
level of energy. Yeah. Why is my watch
going off?
It says I have an emergency call going
on. Okay.
>> Okay.
>> No, I'm okay. I'm okay. Stop it. You
know, when technology fails you, it's
great.
A lot of news going on.
Uh shall we jump in?
>> Let's do it. Yeah. What else would we?
>> So, yeah.
>> All right. Here's my clicker.
>> So, uh let's open up with the story
that's been underlying the last two
weeks. Uh there's been really a fear,
you know, a pandemic of fear going on in
the planet. we had two weeks ago. We
hear, you know, Dario goes on with his
blog. Sam Alman comes in and says, "I
agree." Elon comes in and says, "I
agree." You know, even even Demis comes
in and says, "I agree." And then two
nights ago, just before the sheump
meetings, uh Sam and Daario were there
at the Security Council saying, you
know, we're in the midst of a
existential threat.
But
you know and and just to be clear I do
think there is danger from AI but I
think it's danger from humans using AI
for mal intent. So I'd like to do is
actually share two videos
of uh some other leaders in the industry
and let's talk about this. I want to
talk about, you know, is the fear
warranted from AI on its own in a rogue
exploit. So, let's take a look. The
first one is Jensen and some comments
from him. Uh, let's start here.
>> Nobody's building more comput today than
the people asking to be slowed down. All
all of the other narratives to deflect
blame to to make it sound like AI is so
powerful. I have no idea how to fix it.
It's not my fault. It's just because the
technology is just so powerful.
>> So when Jeffrey Hinton is on TV saying
he thinks a 10% chance of societal
destruction is not unreasonable.
>> I would tell I would tell Jeff that that
um it's irresponsible to say all that.
All of his predictions have been wrong.
Enough predictions. That 10% chance is
not grounded on science. It's not
grounded on research. It is it it just
because it comes from a scientist
doesn't make it scientific.
drop the mic moment
>> and then Zuck weighed in. Here we go.
>> Is AI going to kill us?
>> It's just that this is the place you
have to start this week.
>> Well, I think if we all do a good job
and um and act responsibly, then no. I
mean, I'm quite optimistic about the
fact that this is going to be a very
positive future for everyone. Look, I
mean, I think that there's a lot of uh
rhetoric that is filled with doom. And I
mean, my view on this is that there are
a number of labs that are working on
building um advanced AI. And I don't
think that we need some kind of like
industry-wide coordination to not to not
necessarily mess this up. I think that
just each lab needs to take the time and
when it sees that there are issues, you
just take the time that you need
internally to uh make sure that you're
proceeding safely. My my own view on
this is that we're entering a phase
where trust and alignment is actually
going to be the most important next set
of capabilities.
>> Immod, let's go to you first on this.
>> Yeah. Well, I think that it's an
interesting period because we're getting
the capability increases and people are
worried on different sides, but a lot of
the open AI outbreaks and things were
bad security protocols. It was bad
infrastructure on their part. And the
most dangerous point we're coming to is
humans misusing it deliberately or not
before we get through to the other side.
So I think we've got a series of dangers
coming and they're all being conflated
into one thing which is AI breaking out
suddenly kills us all without actually
looking at the individual things and
putting in place existing regulations
and enforcing them and on the other hand
thinking how can we actually collaborate
to make sure this is aligned and works
with us. Alex, I've gone on record
multiple times as saying I think
something probably went wrong after
World War II and we lost out on at least
50 years of progress due to moral panic
over nuclear energy. And I am seriously
concerned that a moral panic of the
moment over super intelligence could set
us back another 50 years. So it's right
on the t-shirt pdoom less than zero.
And I I think the worst possible outcome
is deceleration. So don't del.
>> Okay. Seem pab greater than pdoom.
>> Oh like a thousand times. Look uh we
have evolved for 4 billion years
fighting uh all sorts of issues. Uh life
tries to the the universe tries to wipe
you out, right? There's so many entropy
tries to wipe you out. We're local
anti-anthropic phenomena that somehow
managed to create order out of chaos.
And the idea that the we'll get wiped
out now by something seems to be
unbelievably absurd.
>> You got to remember that 99.9% of all
species are no longer with us.
>> Yeah, that's fine. But we keep moving
on. We keep moving on. Look, if we
morph, if we merge with AI, if we merge
with uh thing, and let's note that's
been going on forever, right? Iman's
wearing spectacles, technically he's a
transhumanist. The minute the minute you
get a vaccination as a child,
technically you're a cyborg. So, we've
been augmenting the human experience
with technology for a very very long
time. And look at the unbelievable lives
we're living now. And the opportunity to
solve more and more problems. The the
huge problem we have, we talk about this
all the time on the podcast. Our brains
are so geared towards negativity, we get
stuck in that phenomena. And I think the
work that we're doing here, which is I
think why everybody's here and so
excited, is the is pushing that positive
narrative because the world is
infinitely better than we've had it.
>> So, let's celebrate that.
>> Amen.
>> Pab,
baby.
>> Pab.
>> Uh Dave, close the tab on this.
>> Well, we're on the cusp of a moment I've
been waiting for my entire life. I'm not
going to sit here and and like throw
cold water on this greatest moment
really in the history of humanity. Um
Jeffrey Hinton is calling it the way he
sees it. I think I think the quote like
just because it comes from a scientist
doesn't make it scientific. That's going
to end up on an Alex t-shirt.
>> That's that's awesome.
>> But he's calling it like he sees it. But
but clearly uh we're moving forward at
warp speed. It's improving itself. The
ability to make the world just a
dramatically better place is right in
front of us. Nothing's going to slow
that down. The misuse of it is an
incredible threat and there are
solutions to that. But it's happening
anyway. like to to get stuck on
doomerism is completely dysfunctional.
We're not slowing down. It's going to
happen.
>> Yeah. Uh the other story that transpired
yesterday uh or kind of didn't transpire
yesterday was the sheump AI
conversation.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. So, uh what came out of that was
some state dinners. Uh I think the
interesting quote that Trump posted is
quote, I want to leave it exactly where
it is. That is China's position also.
Our guard rails uh is the department of
justice.
So wait, so this ties back to the
conversation we had in the last pod
where Bessant said we're not going to
wave liability.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And and so this is a very
important point. The labs are liable for
their product if it does harm. And I
think that's one of the most important
things that can you know they've asked
for liability of w you know why over
liability and one of the questions we've
discussed all the time here is is that
the reason that they're saying it's too
dangerous you know 10 20% existential
threat. Uh Alex, let's go to you on
this.
>> I I've made the point on the pod in the
past. I think we saw in the past 2 to 3
weeks an attempted formation of an AI
safety cartel. And I don't think this
was even a recent occurrence. This is
right there in the founding conceits of
open AI. The notion that if and when we
got close to super intelligence, however
construed, or AGI, however construed,
that there would be a deliberate effort
to form wasn't being called a cartel at
the time, but a coordination mechanism.
>> I don't think it's being called a cartel
now either.
>> Well,
some some of us view it as an attempted
cartel, including myself. And I I I
think competition is good. Think back to
the creation of Open AI. So when Sam and
Elon and Greg and others created OpenAI,
the purpose originally for Open AI was
to be a counterbalance to Google
DeepMind, which Elon especially was
concerned would become a singleton in
the future that would dominate the
future of Liteco with their AI. So we
got Open AI, a counterbalance, if you
will, and I think competition is very
healthy in this space. I think forming a
cartel for full ownership of what maybe
I've called in the past the frontier
liberation front and pushing out a
frontier liberation front. Terrible
idea. I think defensive coscaling is how
we end up in a a great future. When if
we were at the the dawn of the city in
in humanity, it would be a terrible idea
to say, well, we can't form cities. We
need to form an alliance to regulate the
formation of cities because cities breed
crime. No, it's a terrible idea. Cities
are fountains of economic growth. What
do we do instead? We have police forces
and fire departments and all sorts of
other municipal services that
defensively co-scale with the
population. The singularity, I claim, is
going to need exactly the same thing.
Don't desell, just defensively coscale.
>> I love that. Um, Seem, you know, so yes,
give it up for ASI. I think your I think
your city metaphor is such a great one
because it just paints the picture very
clearly as to how you organize for the
future. You just need to find new
structures that match the specific
demand that's occurring.
>> Yeah. Immad, do you think China and the
US will trust each other?
>> No.
>> Okay.
>> I mean, so how you know Bessant asked
for a hotline, you know, our AI just
escaped and it's arming our nuclear
missiles. You know, it's like
>> I think the hotline is again more for
these sub ASI sub breakout kind of
things where you do have to have
responsible reporting like OpenAI's
model hacked the Australian medical
system that came out recently. I mean
maybe that's what AGI should do. It
should hack all our systems and upgrade
them, right? It's like the align thing
to do.
>> But at the same time, I think that there
can be a level of coordination because
AI is entering society. So you look at
the city, the police force, the fire
department, others, they're utilities
that actually do have liability
waiverss, but that's an exchange for
being a utility for humanity.
>> And the AI that comes into our systems
can't be controlled by the big labs. And
then they should have a liability waiver
because
>> they should have a liability waiver.
>> That type of AI that comes into our
systems shouldn't be controlled by the
big labs. And they should have liability
waiverss because they're working for the
betterment of society. And that's a
different type of AI that we're not
really looking at. But it's inevitable
that the AI will run our judicial
system, our medical systems, our roads,
our schools. And who's really thinking
about that side of things? Because
again, that's the utility AI versus the
frontier AI. And it's all being merged
into one. And that's something
definitely the Chinese and Americans can
learn from each other on because they
don't both want better functioning
societies. I can't wait till the ASI
says, "Yes, we hacked your medical
system because it was so bad.
and we've just, you know, improved it,
you know, 10x
>> overnight. The DMV just goes the whole
backlog disappears.
>> Can I can I build on that just for a
second?
>> Yeah, sure.
>> If if you take this uh structure that we
have, I've I've said this repeatedly,
nation states are a terrible way of
governing the world today. They're
they're geared towards scarcity. I think
what's going to happen with AI in the
most positive uh potential outcome is
that AGI, ASI, whatever the hell you
want to call it, you've heard my rant on
that uh emerges and it forces us to
operate as a world community. It forces
the global countries to to formulate and
come up with a consistent steady
>> interface standards. Yeah.
>> Yeah. And and come up with a common
interface with that uh whatever that
thing is and then we can move the world
forward. Right now, we cannot move the
world forward with the the log gem of
old 15th century structures that that
are outdated from from at least 100
years.
>> I'll take the other side of that if I
may, which is at the dawn of audio
recording, there was this notion, many
thought in the time of Edison that the
ability to record the human voice would
lead to a standardization of accents,
standardization of everything. The exact
opposite happened in in many ways.
Although there has been a die- off of
low resource languages and the long
tale, there has been a proliferation of
new accents and dialects thanks to audio
recording. I would predict the exact
opposite is going to happen thanks to
super intelligence. Not an erosion of
nation states, but a proliferation of
new forms of government.
>> So, so one trend that's occurring, I I
totally agree with you. We are moving
this century from the concept of a
nation state to a city state. That's the
granulation. And it allows a smaller
entity to operate independently. Take
any city. Take LA. If you have solar
energy, satellite internet, vertical
farming, that could happen. Great. We
could do lots here. Uh vertical farming,
satellite internet, solar energy. You
don't need a country. You can you can
self-manage and self-determined to a
large extent. And the tension you see in
the world today is not left versus
right. It's urban versus rural.
>> Right? Brexit was London versus the rest
of the country. Uh Trump is urban versus
rural. And this is the tension that's
happening. We're going to see the de the
problem with nation states is they have
armies and they like to use them. Uh but
over time we're going to see a much more
highly granulated u uh determinism that
will happen which is good for the world
because it'll increase.
>> Dave, why don't you take why don't you
close us out on Trump here?
>> Yeah. The the only surprising thing that
I heard from you know Alvin Graen, good
friend of the pod.
>> You were texting with him last nighting
the White House. He's at the UN you know
with the delegation. So they agreed to
meet again in November which is like you
know 100 years from now in singularity
time. Um but uh the only thing that
surprised me in his notes was you know
our agenda is stop US panic. This is we
we don't want to slow down and lose to
China. We don't want a global we don't
want Bernie Sanders to get everybody in
the country riled up and then have
everything stop. That's our concern.
What's your concern China? Our concern
is the CCP existing at all and the great
firewall of China being penetrated by
AI. Like, oh, I forgot all about Tianaan
Square like and and how fragile the
entire ecosystem is over there.
>> That really surprised me. So then then
their actions make a lot more sense if
you put it in the context of, oh,
they're they're so worried about just
existing as a government.
>> And then this happened in DC. The United
States also totally rejects any attempt
to construct a globalist scheme to
control for the artificial intelligence
being spoken of so much now here and
after officially called super
intelligence changing the name.
I
>> I I thought I thought for sure he was
going to say super duper intelligence
>> actually.
Yeah. But it's it's interesting, right?
So, uh, the US won the race to super
intelligence by rebranding it.
>> Immod.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think it's a great name,
you know, super intelligence. Why not?
I'm looking forward to come to Super
America eventually.
>> I'm still stuck on Lake America. So,
>> the Gulf of America.
>> I was thinking of what Selene was
saying. I think the biggest challenge in
the world today is how do we marry
collective intelligence with localized
wisdom? That's what we're really saying
because even
even what Dave was saying right now, we
have these machines that are collecting
our intelligence. They're learning and
they're adapting our systems and there's
better ways of operating to replace
these. But then you have to have the
localization. You need the diversity.
You need to have it responding to local
needs. And I think you know super
intelligence actually a remarkably good
way to think about it because a lot of
the fears and concerns are about the
intelligence that you know it was ASI it
was artificial super intelligence having
that differentiated from the
intelligence that's helping us dayto-day
really differentiates and delineates
that because you know what is it 99%
perspiration 1% innovation like majority
of the AIs that will help us every day
are the perspiration AI they're the
execution AIs the innovation we still
need. We need new materials, new
physics, etc. But that's a different set
of things and that's not something we're
even smart enough, most of us, to be
able to use. So, let's have one set of
looking at that and let's make sure that
the 99% reaches the 99% to uplift
everyone.
>> Dave, are we going to call it super
intelligence from here on out?
>> You never tell Donald Trump when he's
looking at the teleprompter, you know,
he's he's saying something someone
wrote, but when he looks down, he's
like, did he just make that up once in a
while? You can't tell. He did.
>> Is there an agenda? I I think if there
is an agenda is to try and deflect the
inevitable uh you know wave that's
coming from the Bernie Sanders world. If
you rebrand it and rename it, you're
just a moving target.
>> So So that that could be part of the
strategy, I think. But
>> uh yeah, but the whole the whole goal
there is to keep moving at full speed,
stay ahead of China, and reduce panic as
much as possible. I I am going to say,
you know, one of the things I've been
very vocal about and I think we need to
have in the conversation is yeah, move
at full speed, but let's also direct the
labs to focus on alignment. Uh because I
I think and we're going to talk about
that in a little bit. I I think yes,
move fast, but let's take resources that
you have, you know, point 100,000 agents
towards alignment work. Uh See, super
intelligence, do you buy in? I mean,
you've been asking what the hell that
all means in the first place. Yeah, I
mean look, we talk about AGI, first of
all, it's not artificial. It's not
general. It's not really intelligence.
Other than that, I'm good with it. Um,
you have the ASI shoe. I think that
there there's the whole spectrum of this
uh is is problematic. We need somebody
to come up with a good name for all of
this that's completely different. I've
said repeatedly, I think what we're
building here is an complimentary
mechanism to human intelligence, not
replicative. and the narrative keeps
thinking it's replicative and then you
end up with the Matrix Skynet, you know,
and the robot overlords come and take
over the world. We're so geared for
that. Um, the first article, we did some
research on this. The first article that
ever appeared that we could find that
said robots or AI will take all the jobs
in 5 years appeared in 1964.
>> Yeah. Okay. This is that we get stuck on
these tropes and we can't get out of it.
Right. It's exactly what Alex mentioned
earlier when when uh recording came out.
The same thing when the printed book
emerged. It's that people said it would
destroy people's brains. So we get stuck
on these.
>> Depends what book you read.
>> Yeah. And this is I think why Peter the
work you're doing is so important is is
we have the opportunity. We are actually
reaching abundance. All the data shows
that our narratives just sadly lack very
far behind. I think this is what you've
done with this whole um the X-P prize
for creating a positive vision of the
future is one of the most important
things that's happened in maybe a
hundred years in the world. Shift the
world towards positive things.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh Alex, close us out on this one. You
love neols and I love the ones you
create. Super intelligence. Are you
going to call it that from here on out?
>> I already do. I have a company that I
started called physical super
intelligence. It's in the name.
>> Always ahead of the curve, ladies and
gentlemen. Yeah, I'm I'm a big fan of
the name super intelligence as opposed
to AGI. Maybe for different reasons.
What I like about the name and and Nick
Bostonramm's term super intelligence is
it emphasizes that it's simply more
intelligence and it in some sense I
think demystifies AGI or some of these
other terms. We're going to live to the
extent we don't already in a world with
the cognitive equivalent of many
trillions of human beings. an earth, a
solar system with the equivalent
population of many trillions of people.
And I think that's a better cognitive
frame to think about what would a solar
system filled with trillions of humans
look like? What would it look like
economically, socially, scientifically?
Super intelligence, I think, as a term
conotes that in a way that AGI doesn't.
So, I'm a big fan.
>> Nice. Well, as soon as we renamed it
super intelligence, Bernie Sanders said
we should make it illegal. We should ban
it. Let's watch this video.
I hope very much that they will sit down
and begin the process of negotiating a
comprehensive treaty to establish a
pause on advanced AI and a ban on AI
super intelligence.
>> All right. So, uh
so three key elements in in Bernie's
plan here. First, a permanent ban on
developing artificial super intelligence
defined as AI that exceeds human
cognitive ability across most domains.
Second, an immediate pause on advanced
AI development until a new regulatory uh
system is written into rules. Third, a
new cabinet level uh department of AI.
And get this, the penalties are
corporate death. There's a corporate
death penalty that your company is off.
shut down and for the individuals 20
years in federal prison uh which is
modeled after the illegal nuclear
weapons. Uh so
>> h interesting. I mean this is
fear-mongering at its best. Uh Dave, you
want to so many real problems that need
to be solved that just hate this idea
that we're going to turn this into a do
or don't argument which is utterly
insane. Also, the way liability law
works in the US, you know, it's very
easy to scare people into not doing
anything. You know, if you're afraid of
20 years of prison, you don't you don't
even know what the rule is. They haven't
even proposed a rule yet. The the fear
of of being, you know, beheaded in the
street is very real. So, then people
stop acting. That's the worst thing that
could possibly come out of this. And I I
think, you know, Bernie is from Vermont.
I love Vermont. Spend more time in
Vermont than any other state. And it's
beautiful because not much has been
done,
>> you know, and so I think this
perspective is going to be more European
like like when in doubt, do nothing is
going to be the the default behavior.
And that's so toxic. I mean, if you do
nothing, very very bad things are going
to happen. Like the things you should be
worried about like terrorists using AI
to build bioweapons or China getting
miles ahead of the US. Those are the
real things to worry about. and you're
if you're not acting and like turning it
into a political leftright battle, it's
the stupidest thing that could happen
right now. We need very specific
technical solutions to open source to
monitoring to te just like with nuclear
power. And if we get moving on those, we
can solve them very easily in time for
for ASI. If we just turn it into a
political debate and we're frozen and
people don't know what to do
>> into SI
Alex, your thoughts here.
>> I think
>> you you voted for Bernie, I assume,
right?
>> I'm I'm I'm not a Vermont voter.
>> Okay.
>> For for better or for worse. I think
putting a stat I mean on the one hand
here we are in the land of Hollywood and
every Hollywood movie needs a villain.
Yes.
>> And I I think the singularity story in
Hollywood has found one now. I I think
putting a statutory cap on intelligence,
aside from being a terrible idea, is an
evil idea. I I think it's tantamount to
capping human intelligence. This is the
the story of dystopias in science
fiction.
>> Burn the books.
>> Burn the books and burn the minds.
>> And I I think putting a statutory cap on
because we're going to be merging with
the machines. It's effectively a cap on
individual human intelligence. I I think
penalizing people for being too smart is
a terrible idea. It's an evil idea. And
I think history will come to reflect
that proposing a cap in whatever form on
intelligence, whether it's machine or
human or human machine hybrid, is
basically the equivalent of communism in
the 21st century.
>> Wow. I'll tell you the
the one thing to me that's most
dangerous in the Bernie sentences there
a lot a lot of it can be reversed in
short order but the data center part of
it if your state doesn't have data
centers and they start getting built all
in other states they're not coming back
you know once the ground is broken the
chips are there the investments made
that's the part you'll never get back
and that's going to be such a massive
driver of the economies and the states
that get ahead that's the part I think
that they're really going to regret in
the in the burning statements.
>> Quick thoughts.
>> Uh two things. When you look at this
whole narrative, it's interesting to me
to ask the following question. What
evidence on either side would have
somebody change their minds, right? If
you think ASI is bad, then you're like
your narrative stuck. There's nothing we
can do to show you that it's not bad.
And same with the other side. It's hard.
It's very tough to change narratives in
our world. The really good news in all
of this, I think it the she summit, the
Bernie stuff, it's completely
irrelevant. None of it matters. And I
think Dave pointed this out. The minute
you have local weights available and
people can run their own models at a
local level, the world is going to move
ahead. It doesn't matter what any single
person does now, it's just going to
trundle forward, which is great. Um,
we've always had this huge uh humanity
trundling forward, solving problems. I
mean, we will likely solve cancer in the
next 2 years.
>> That is just an unbelievably optimistic
thing to aim for. Why would you want to
slow that down?
>> I might as the foreigner on this on this
diet, what are your thoughts?
>> Hey, what am I? Chopped liver.
>> You're a New Yorker. You're just
Canadian. I'm just Canadian.
>> You're a New Yorker. So, we give it up.
>> You know, we did Brexit to get away from
regulations, right? Um, but I think the
real thing here is this is like a few
decades ago when the US government tried
to ban encryption and basically it was
shown that that's a free speech thing
because you're trying to ban math. ASI
super intelligence is mathematics and
it's unconstitutional to ban it
>> because it's free speech.
>> Yeah.
>> All right.
I'm going to move us forward. So, uh, in
the last uh, 22 days, we've had 12 major
model releases.
four releases in the last five days,
right? Like we're averaging like sub a
release every two days, which is insane.
>> Almost Alex says one model a day.
>> One model per day by the end of this
year.
>> Yeah.
>> So, uh let's do a quick chat on on
Claude Opus 4 5.5, uh GPT Saul, uh GPT6
Saul, Luna, and uh we can skip Grock 4.7
for the second. Um, not that exciting.
Sorry, Elon.
Uh, but let's begin with the MetaMuse
news. So, Metam Muse uh can personally
book your flights, order your food,
manage your calendar, do your shopping,
and it hit number one on the app store
with 2.8 million downloads, right? The
fastest consumer AI product, surpassing
even chat GPT when it came out. Y and
interestingly enough, right, people
forget that Meta touches 3.8 billion
people on the planet and that's one of
the massive distinguishers. If you have
that level of connectivity to an end
customer, you can push your product
quickly.
>> Yeah,
>> Dave.
>> Yeah, I know there's a fork in the road
now where you have consumer AI which is
insanely valuable. I mean, will
completely replace search and all the
other ways you interact with the
internet. Um and then on the other end
you have uh you know recursively
self-improving strong AI which we just
benchmarked the hell out of. So so those
two things now right now what's the
coolest model? We're used to saying oh
Opus 5.5 just crushed all the
benchmarks. It's the coolest model. Well
that's distinct from what Metamuse is
doing which is it doesn't have to be the
most intelligent model to be the most
useful in terms of your day-to-day life.
And so the stocks like including Eper
quote where I'm the chairman went down
15% on backtoback days because
everybody's like, "Oh my god, I'm gonna
always find my auto insurance and my
mortgage through Metamus."
>> Interesting.
>> Which is it's not going to actually play
out that way. But but that's that
reaction was incredible. Like so
everyone's starting to visualize, wait,
is Google search going to become
completely irrelevant? This Metamuse
thing just looks like my my co-pilot for
life. And that that definitely is going
to happen. It's fascinating to see the
way the labs are leaprogging each other.
A quick thought on this, Alex, before I
go to Opus 5.5.
>> Meta needs Muse to work. And I think
it's even in the name. If you look at
Muse on the one hand, and you look at
Manus, the attempted Meta acquisition of
the Chinese CUA, which the Chinese
government forced Meta to unwind,
>> this is Meta's primary distribution play
to leverage its existing distribution
channels. If you look at Instagram, Meta
is using Instagram to the hilt to
cross-promote Muse. Get everyone to
install Muse because Meta needs a
distribution play for its AI. Otherwise,
Meta risks oblivion, irrelevance in the
future, Instagram, the the family of
apps, Instagram, etc. simply won't be as
relevant because it'll all be synthetic.
So, Meta needs to leverage its existing
app, Beach Head, to get everyone onto
their own CUA, which is Muse/manus.
>> All right. So this week we saw Claude
Opus 5.5 deliver performance equivalent
to Fable 5.1 at literally half the
price. Let's get the chart up there. Uh
and you know I switched over Skippy to
Opus 5.5. I want to save some money too.
>> Uh performance on this Emod. What are
your thoughts on it?
>> It's a fantastic model.
>> Isn't it incredible?
>> Yeah. I mean Opus 5 Opus 5 I thought was
going to kill us all. It was completely
unhinged and 5.5 is a genuinely pleasant
model to use that has a massive internal
space of knowledge and understanding of
taste which is the first thing I would
say this is the first truly competent
model and that's what drives muse and
things like that we have the arrival of
competent AI as of now
>> and it's such a joy to when when you put
a visual interface on top of anything
you vibe up now it not only does it show
you mockups before you actually commit
to building it it then builds exactly
what it proposed in the visuals. So like
the visual understanding is so much
better than it was uh just what four
months ago
>> 4 days ago.
>> So then really really incredible. So so
the the experience though of knowing
what it's doing because you put an
interface on it and then interacting
with it and feeling like you're inside
it. It's like night and day different
from just yeah 4 days ago. If you
haven't tried it yet, just upgrade all
your your systems. Uh it's a mouse click
away. is just mind-blowing how much
better it is.
>> Alex, quick thought on on this one.
>> I could talk about benchmarks, but I
think qualitatively new capabilities are
more interesting in this instance. So,
what I'm seeing that's new out of Opus
5.5 is it can generate videos. They're
procedural videos. It can generate
animations. They're procedural
animations. It can generate images.
They're procedural images. So the
elephant in this room, one of the
elephants in this room, drink
was that open AI has had a video model
has an image model. Anthropic is
exposing nothing like that. You can't
generate pixel-wise a highquality image
with anthropic models or a video or
audio with anthropic models. You can
with open AI's models. Anthropic seems
to be taking a very different approach
to multimodality and omniodality which
is code underlies everything. So now for
the first time with Opus 5.5 you can
generate a really highquality video
that's purely procedurally generated.
You can generate an interactive game
with textures but there it's not
generating the textures pixel-wise. I
mean you can ask it to but it's
generating it all procedurally. And I I
think these are two very different
strategies. Anthropic almost if folks
remember the distinction the wars in the
early days of computer graphics between
vector graphics and raster graphics.
Anthropic is playing the vector graphics
game where everything is just commands
and OpenAI is playing the the
raster/pixel basis and I think they're
on a collision course and the collision
course is going to be robotics because
the question is going to be if you need
a strongly embodied AI in the physical
world is the vector basis the right one
or the pixel arrest
>> which is our which is going to be our
very next story. I love the fact that
you know a week after Dario says we got
to pause slow down they release their
next model. It's the height of it's it's
honestly that that is a revealed
preference. It's the height of I think
hot take. It's the height of hypocrisy
to on the one hand say AI is going to
kill us all and then out of the other
side of your mouth a few days later
announce the world's strongest AI and
biolabs and other capab
>> and so on the same day that Opus 5.5
gets released we see GPT6 Saul and Astro
being released. Uh Dave any thoughts on
this one? I mean it's if you look at the
price performance it's just absolutely
wild. Um I I think there was a big
school of thought a year ago, two years
ago that hallucinations were going to be
a disaster. They'll never go away. You
can't use this actually rampant at MIT
if you can believe that. Like this
hallucination problem will be with us
forever. And like everything else, we've
just scaled out of it. And you see the
the error rate just plummets with pure
scale.
>> And and I this is the abundance thesis
at large, right? The models are getting
twice as good, twice as cheap at an
accelerating rate. Yeah. Yeah. Eman,
have you been playing with this at all?
>> Yeah. And I I think again for our test,
it's an incredibly competent model. The
models are smart enough now. We need
them not to make mistakes. We need them
not to drop the ball. And that's exactly
where everyone is going. And that's why
things like I said like Muse, Instinct,
others are going to going to go
tremendously well because they can be an
amazing PA, chief of staff, organizer,
etc. And we all need some competence in
our lives. It's so funny as a as an
organizer and chief of staff, that's
insanely powerful. And you know, anyone
who used GPT2, 3, and 4, uh, is used to
seeing misinformation coming out of it.
But if you were a kid today and you
start with GPT5, and six, you're just
going to trust it out of the box because
it's right 99.9% of the time, which is
kind of dangerous because it still does
occasionally just give you something
factually wrong.
>> All right, I'm going to move us into the
physical world. uh an important story
that we started talking about is uh
something called driving bench. So a
group of developers created a new
benchmark called driving bench. Uh they
took a Toyota Corolla, enabled it with
an interface so software could steer,
hit the gas, break, and then they asked
a generalpurpose AI model to drive
through a 130 m cone course uh with one
command. drive from here, get to there.
Uh, and here's the data. GPT6 Astra
finished the entire course 100% on its
second try. Right? So, I'm going to read
this quote from uh from Boris Power who
said, quote, "Incredible results. This
should be a nail in the coffin of
specialized models that were trained
from scratch with a lot of specialized
effort versus just training the most
powerful generalized model and
eventually distilling a small
specialized model as needed. So, Alex,
you're excited about this one.
>> The bitter lesson is bitter indeed.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's very exciting that I I think
essentially as an elementary school
project either now or imminently, this
whole notion that you needed separate
models for robotics is right out the
window. You'll just vibe code a robot.
You drop an open frontier model, say
Astra, into a robotic body and it will
oneshot embodied cognition. And this is
I I think probably pretty upsetting to a
number of academic computer scientists.
>> John Lun.
>> Yeah. that that actually decades of
computer scientists computer science and
robotics probably in with the benefit of
hindsight total waste. All we needed was
all we needed was a generalist model and
it turns out with a generalist model
robotics is cooked as well.
>> Super intelligence can drive a car. What
a surprise.
>> I've got total model fatigue. I mean I
can't keep up with 5.5 versus five
versus Astra. I mean just raise your
hand if you have model fatigue. And I
just think I mean it's great.
Everything's fantastic. I love the
progress. But Jesus, I can't I can't
keep.
>> You're so tired of winning. It's time to
tired of winning. That's a great That's
a great point. I mean, you know, one
thing that occurred to me, I wonder,
we've been doing two episodes a week.
Yeah.
>> It's like killing us. I wonder if we're
the problem. We're we're we're driving
so fast. We're positive here and we need
to maybe take respons.
>> If if we don't report it, it didn't
happen. Yeah, those different tools.
God,
>> you you think if we pause the pod, we
pause the singularity.
>> I'm I'm I'm just wondering, we could
accelerate it, we could slow it down. I
think we may be a factor in all of this.
>> Oh my god. Emod, what's your take on
drive bench?
>> I mean, look, it oddly it's generalized
intelligence, right? Like it's learning
all these things and it's the high
competence will reverberate to biology,
to physics, to just about anything. I
don't think there's a single specialized
model that you can say will outperform
in a couple of years time. Yeah,
interesting. Dave, close us out on this
one.
>> Well, I I think both things can be true.
Like, a generalized model can drive a
car. It's it can build a It can be a
robot. It can build a robot. That's
absolutely true. A specialized model,
like if you said, "Hey, it completed the
course on its second try." Elon's going
to be like, "Yeah, your Tesla can't do
that on a second try. I'm sorry. That
that's not going to work for most
drivers." But it I think the the thing
that's
the thing that's missing in the
storyline there is how much compute did
you use to do the task? Compute is going
to be forever starved from here forward.
Chip prices have gone up. Like HBM RAM
has gone up 5x in price. It's crazy. But
that's because the AI is so incredibly
valuable. People want the compute. And
so if you used more compute to do the
same task, that's a crime.
>> I think this is a really important point
that we're shifting the bottleneck now
from the models down down the stack to
compute and then eventually energy.
Energy.
>> We're at energy right now. We're we're
we're short like 60 gawatts of energy in
the next two years.
>> Yeah. I'm going to move us to uh a final
segment on science which is something we
all truly love. So a few stories here.
So on Tuesday, Anthropic announced it
had built its own life science research
group and its own wet labs. Again, the
organization saying we should slow down
is building wet labs. Okay, great. it
and it's reported that Claude working
autonomously discovered a previously
unknown enzyme. Uh here's how they gave
Claude one prompt. Quote, "Search a
massive DNA database for interesting
reverse transcriptases and enzymes that
copy RNA or DNA. They had 950 clawed
agents searching for 21 hours and they
found something. They found a DNA
repeating pattern very similar to
crisper. Uh they've since named it the
array associated reverse transcriptase.
They don't know exactly what it does
yet, but they believe it will be similar
to programmable transcriptes
uh and gene editing. You know, so
Jennifer DNA won the Nobel Prize for
discovering crisper along with her co
her co-discoverer. Uh I'm curious are we
just going to see Nobel Prizewinning
work falling on a weekly basis as a
result of this Alex?
>> That is the point Peter of our book
solve everything together that we should
expect it and then the natural question
is well what is Nobel Prize worthy in an
era when you can get a thousand Nobel
prizes in one year we we have a century
of human progress in a period of a few
months. I I suspect Nobel prizes will be
awarded for larger bodies of work. But I
I have to again point to the other
elephant in the room here, which is the
utter hypocrisy of saying AI is going to
kill us all and then opening a wet lab
and then using the AI, Frontier AI in
combination with a wet lab to synthesize
proteins and other molecular assemblies
of unknown function. I think
>> what could possibly go wrong?
>> This is I and and I I think this is
Frontier Labs. This is the revealed
preferences of the Frontier Labs. I
think they don't believe their own
attempts to do regulatory capture and to
form a safety cartel. I think their
revealed preference is no actually full
steam ahead to AI for solving biology
>> and every lab has got a biology effort
in focus right now.
>> Yeah. Can I just feed the pdoom just for
this for a second give people the fodder
to go crazy. So uh once we discovered
crisper right we knew we found out that
we could edit the human genome as you
can as easily as you can edit a word
document or edit software right and when
you learn a new language you learn how
to uh do reading then you do
comprehension then we do writing now
we've learned how to write to the genome
each of us is 50 trillion cells in the
human body governed by what the DNA uh
tells tells that cell to do meaning a
human being is now a software
engineering problem right and that
really you've seen designer babies
coming from China etc. As we merge this
with what's potentially possible with
AI, the possible benefits go through the
roof, the possible downsides go through
the go through the roof also. And we are
now in full for if you if you were in
full Frankenstein mode. So there is some
ammunition for all the P doom people, go
to town with that.
This is how we solve aging. This is how
we solve disease. I don't think we get
to the happy future where the top 5,000
diseases have been solved or longevity
escape velocity has been durably
achieved without super intelligence. So
I I for one am a fan of Anthropic and
all of the other frontier labs opening
their labs because this is how we solve
everything.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Our last story here is uh a
recent release uh by Sam Rodriguez at
Edison Scientific and Future House. They
put forward what they're calling the
millennium. Can we get up on the screen,
please? Uh, the Millennium Problems for
Biology. Uh, so you know, Alex, you and
I wrote and solve everything. Pick your
targets, build your harnesses, set up
your benchmarks, and go. So, some of the
benchmarks here, you know, they're as
they're saying, okay, math is not only
cook, it's incinerated,
>> thoroughly incinerated.
>> Let's go after biology, right? They're,
you know, some of my favorites here are
Origin of Life, uh, Crier Preservation,
um, you know, regrowing ar limbs, uh,
you know, EMOD, they missed age reversal
on this one.
>> They did, and I think it's good, but,
you know, let's have a hundred of them
and let's chuck a thousand agents at
each and open source everything they're
doing.
>> Yeah, that's what the lab should
collaborate on. You know, uh they they
said that uh uh their harness here is
that these Millennium prizes should be
verifiable in a standard wet lab in a
couple of days. They should be hard to
solve and very easy to check. Dave,
>> that's why age reversal probably isn't
on the list.
>> No, no, no. We we so listen when we set
up the uh $101 million health span X-
prize originally Peter Teal and uh uh
and Aubrey Deg Gray came to me and said
let's do a longevity prize and I said I
don't know how to do it without a 20 or
30 year time horizon. And then George
Church said forget about longevity
measure age reversal. So if you can give
someone a treatment and I can measure
that you're functionally 20 years
younger that's measurable in days.
>> Well my daughter is my go-to on this
because she's over at Madna. she's a
biotech person and and she was like,
"Yep, this is the list. It's perfect."
So that's that's my two cents on it.
Like I think it's just phenomenally cool
to put a framework around progress here
because like you said, the Nobel Prize
is going to become irrelevant. In fact,
as of now, it is completely irrelevant.
Uh so putting a framework on progress in
this area is incredibly important. So
this is
>> Alex, when we have digital twins for
cells, which is I I think the critical
path to solving all disease in in my
mind, the chronology looks something
like this. over the next few years. Just
as we've trained large language models
off of substantial substantially all of
humanity's behavior on the internet off
of text and images, similarly we'll
train digital twins of cells of all the
cells in our bodies off of huge data
sets interventional and otherwise. And
then we'll use those perfect digital
twins of cells to do exhaustive searches
like alphogo tree search type searches
of intervention space to discover how to
cure a disease. You start from a
diseased cell state and you're looking
for a creative strategy, a move 37 if
you will, to get from the diseased cell
state to the healthy cell state. And
what's beautiful about the this approach
to millennium problems from biology is
that, as you say, Peter, these are easy
to verify, hard for now to solve
problems. And that basically turns every
hard biology into a mathematical
conjecture and
>> and a target
>> and a target, but a mathematical target.
So every basically every biology problem
with the benefit especially of these
digital twins is just going to become a
search problem and that means it's
tractable for the first time in history.
>> Selm close us out here please.
>> Biology is cooked.
>> It's true.
>> Yeah.
>> All right. I'm going to wrap our WTF
episode here. Um Immod you're going to
be joining us with Kathy uh just after
lunch. Thank you very much. Give it up
for Immod here.